[Music] In
June 2023,
more than 300 people died
and more than 900 were injured in a train accident in Odisha.
Another shocking news in this train accident was
that only 22
claims were made by insurance companies
and none of the claims were for disability.
This train accident was very
painful and who knows how many families and
people must have become financially unstable in this.
Now we will look at some health-related statistics
which are in India. If we
compare health insurance penetration,
only 37 percent people have health insurance in India
and in the US, 92.1 percent
people have health insurance, which is
many times more. So we should
increase awareness about health insurance in India
and the government supports health insurance.
If you take any health
insurance, you
get tax benefits. If we talk about medical inflation, according to the
Business Standard
report, medical inflation is 14
to 15 percent per year.  If a
treatment is being done for ₹1 lakh today, then the same will cost ₹
114000 or 000 next year. When our medical
cost is increasing and so many diseases are increasing in day to day life,
for this we should take a good health insurance.
When you take any health insurance,
you should always keep some things in mind.
When you take health insurance,
you should get the facility you need.
You should get all the facilities for which you paid. So
you should always take a good health
insurance after doing research. The first important thing is that
whenever you take health insurance, you should
first ask your executive whether the
health insurance you are taking
provides cashless service in your locality
or not. Suppose you travel to two places,
you live in two places, then
make sure that the
health insurance is giving you cashless facility at both the places.
This will be the first thing. The second important thing is
which health
insurance you should take, family floater or
individual. You should always take family floater.  You should take it
if your parents are older, then
you should take a separate family
floater health insurance for them. If you,
your wife and your children are older, then you should take your own
separate family floater because if your
parents' age is higher, then your premium will
increase, so you should take two separate health
insurances, separate for your parents
and separate for your wife and children.
Whenever we talk about health insurance policy, the first thing that
comes to mind is whether it will be
with us in our tough times or not, so
for this you should take health insurance from Policy Bazaar only,
its advantage is
that any executive of Policy Bazaar will
come and help you, so
you will get support because
in your tough times, when any of your family
members falls ill, then you are
not able to settle, so you should always check
with any Policy Bazaar executive and it will be better that you do your
research as well. So what you have to do for this is
whichever company's
health insurance you are taking, you should
not take it blindly, you have to check it.  The claim settlement ratio of the
company whose health insurance you are taking should be
more than 90% and you can check this on the
IRDA website. The fourth thing we have to
check is zero deduction towards
non-medical expenses. What are the items of non-medical expenses, be it
gloves, cotton,
linen, laundry cleaning, all these are
included in our non-medical expenses. So,
check carefully in your terms and conditions that the non-
medical expenses are included in zero deduction. The
fifth thing you have to check is
OPD expenses. You have to check
carefully whether OPD expenses are included in it or
not. If not, then you have to take such health
insurance in which OPD expenses are
included because OPD means you have to get yourself checked
at a day care and come back on the same day. So,
you have to check carefully
whether OPD is included or not. The most important thing is the
waiting period for any disease.  The
standard waiting period is 30 days.
You should go to your terms and conditions
and check what is the waiting period. You should
also check
what is the critical illness waiting period. If you suddenly fall
ill after taking the insurance, will the
insurance company insure you or
not? You have to make sure
in the terms and conditions or you
can easily ask the executive. The seventh thing is
room rent. Whenever you are hospitalized,
1% of your sum assured will be the
room rent. So you have to be
careful that your % is not exceeded.
Otherwise, the insurance company will not pay you
and you can do another thing. You can
take such a policy in which there is no limit on room rent. So,
you should
decide in advance what you have to do, whether to take 1%
or not. Otherwise, the
insurance company will not pay and
you will have to pay from your pocket. The eighth thing is the
list of excludes. Whenever you
take health insurance, you have to check
your  You should
ask the executive to give you the list of
exclusions and check
which are the diseases for which the
insurance company is not going to pay. There will be
a list in it and the
names of all the diseases will be there, so ask your executive for that
thing which you should check.
Whatever health insurance you are taking,
if you get the treatment done in your network hospital only, does it
provide cashless facility there
or you can get it done from some outside hospital
because when you fall sick, you
can be anywhere, it is not necessary that there is a
network hospital where you have taken health insurance,
you will have to get your treatment done in an outside hospital also,
so you have to make sure
that if you get it done from an outside hospital, then
that money will be reimbursed to you and
not by the insurance company, so this is a very
important thing which you have to keep in mind. While
taking health insurance,
you have to check
what is the waiting period for slow growing diseases, like any
slow growing disease like diabetes,
thyroid and stone.  If all this happens
after you take insurance, then
all these come under slow growing diseases,
so the insurance company has fixed a waiting period,
which is generally 24 months.
While taking insurance, you have to keep in mind
how much is the waiting period for slow growing diseases.
You have seen till here, so I will give you a
pro tip, when you
take health insurance, you
can make a mistake at that time, you
can take any health insurance in a hurry, so
what you have to do is you have a free lock-in period of 15 days,
you should read the terms and conditions of your health insurance in that 15 days
because many things are hidden in small words,
so you should
read it in 15 days, if you do
not like your health insurance, then you can
cancel your health insurance within 15 days and
take some other health insurance,
so you can easily buy a good health
insurance after that. When I was
taking health insurance, I was very
confused that I should buy health insurance.
Should I take insurance or not? I already have corporate
health insurance. So what I did was,
I did research and selected a good health
insurance. If you want to know
which health insurance I have taken, then
you can join the membership and from there
you can check
which health insurance I have taken for myself personally.
If you liked my video, then
subscribe to my channel and
like the video and do
not forget to share it with your family and friends. Thank you
so much.